<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>EthicalAds</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.ethicalads.io/</id><updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>EthicalAds Newsletter - February 2021</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2021/03/ethicalads-newsletter-february-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2021-03-08:/blog/2021/03/ethicalads-newsletter-february-2021/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="february-advertising-stats"&gt;February advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February was our best month ever for advertising.
Despite being a shorter month, we were still able …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="february-advertising-stats"&gt;February advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February was our best month ever for advertising.
Despite being a shorter month, we were still able to beat our previous bests from &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2021/02/ethicalads-newsletter-january-2021/"&gt;January&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2021:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We generated &lt;strong&gt;$23,854.36&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers.
  Of this, $11,671.47 was publishers other than our own publisher (Read the Docs) which is a 5.5% increase over January.
  Going forward, we're going to report these numbers together.
  In March and beyond, we expect the revenue to outside publishers will surpass revenue to our own site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;106 publishers&lt;/strong&gt; on our network with a paid ad impression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;13,600,740&lt;/strong&gt; paid ad views across the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're working hard to grow revenue for all our publishers, and we're expecting another record month in March.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-features"&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the major features we added in the last month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the business side, we released our &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/prospectus/ethicalads-advertiser-prospectus.pdf"&gt;Q2 prospectus&lt;/a&gt;
  which contains some of our new testimonials and some small additions like mentioning that CPC-based pricing is available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On our ad client, we rolled out our dark mode improvements
  built on &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/@media/prefers-color-scheme"&gt;&lt;code&gt;prefers-color-scheme&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  to our beta client which is used by Read the Docs. This means sites that want to try it out can do so.
  Some Sphinx documentation themes already are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On our ad server, we improved a few reports (notably a report required by &lt;a href="https://acceptableads.com/"&gt;Acceptable Ads&lt;/a&gt;)
  and made some tweaks to speed up our throughput.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In our infrastructure, we're really pushing the I/O on our server which is writing tens of times per second.
  We worked to try to alleviate some of this pressure and that will continue into March.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While not strictly ads related, Read the Docs did extend an offer to a new person to join our team!
  More on that later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see our latest updates in our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-server.readthedocs.io/en/latest/developer/changelog.html"&gt;ethical-ad-server changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tricky-bits"&gt;Tricky bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still aim to hire a part-time &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/jobs/account-manager-part-time/"&gt;account manager&lt;/a&gt;
to help manage advertiser and publisher relationships.
Hiring is always hard and takes a lot of time to do well.
If this role sounds interesting to you,
please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@ethicalads.io?subject=Ads%20account%20manager%20role"&gt;get in touch with any questions&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/jobs/account-manager-part-time/"&gt;apply&lt;/a&gt;!
In addition, Read the Docs is hiring a &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/job-frontend/"&gt;frontend developer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure will continue to cause some headaches in the next few months.
Read the Docs Community completed a move from Azure to AWS in February
and EthicalAds will probably follow suit in the next few months.
In addition, we've been hitting I/O limits as I mentioned above and while we've made improvements there
and our latency is pretty darn good, we still want to do more.
Our data points pretty directly to faster ads performing better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-features"&gt;Upcoming features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major features in our upcoming roadmap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want to give both advertisers and publishers high level data right in their dashboard when they first login.
  These are stats like exactly how much advertising money they've spent or earned this month
  and how this month compares with last month.
  This feature is still on our roadmap but we didn't wrap it up in February.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're going to expand our advertising logic to take into account price when selecting ads.
  One advertiser has agreed to be a flex advertiser with part of their ad buys in Q2
  which will give them lower prices but not guaranteed inventory.
  This helps us ensure that as many ad slots have paid ads for our publishers while letting us balance our inventory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One publisher agreed to try out EthicalAds for some custom ad placements with non-standard sizes
  and per-month pricing rather than CPM.
  We have begun pitching this to advertisers and we may build some additional features to better support this based on interest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for being along with us on this journey to build an ethical ad network.
Please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@ethicalads.io"&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt; if you have any ideas or feedback on our product or roadmap,
we always love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>Can you Eliminate Annoying Cookie Banners from your Site?</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2021/02/can-you-eliminate-annoying-cookie-banners-from-your-site/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-22T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2021-02-22:/blog/2021/02/can-you-eliminate-annoying-cookie-banners-from-your-site/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Even before the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) went into effect in 2018
with its cookie consent policy, internet users …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Even before the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) went into effect in 2018
with its cookie consent policy, internet users have had unavoidable pop-up messages
thrust onto their screens on every page urging them to "accept all" cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving aside for a moment how that has conditioned people to discard their privacy with a single click,
the experience is challenging on laptops. On mobile, it can be especially painful
with the cookie banner often occupying the majority of the smartphone's screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="width: 300px; margin: 2rem auto;"&gt;
  &lt;img class="w-100" src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2021-cookie-banners-ft-example.png" alt="A cookie banner on the Financial Times taking up about half the screen"&gt;
  &lt;p class="text-center"&gt;&lt;small&gt;A cookie banner on the Financial Times taking up about half the screen&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-exactly-are-these-cookie-banners-needed"&gt;Why exactly are these cookie banners needed?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/cookies/"&gt;EU's GDPR&lt;/a&gt; requires that web sites get consent from visitors &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; setting any non-essential cookies.
"Non-Essential Cookies" are those that are not strictly required for your site to function.
For example, a cookie to keep you logged in may be essential but an analytics cookie from a third-party would not be.
&lt;a href="https://www.oag.ca.gov/privacy/ccpa"&gt;California's Consumer Privacy Act&lt;/a&gt; (CCPA) requires only that visitors be notified of the use of cookies
if they are used for the purpose of collecting personal information; consent is not required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-can-a-site-eliminate-cookie-banners"&gt;How can a site eliminate cookie banners?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is simple in theory, but can be difficult depending on how your site works.
If you don't collect personal information or allow third parties to collect personal information
and you only set essential cookies,
you will not need to set a cookie banner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most sites, the cookies that trigger the laws and violate user privacy are advertising cookies
and website analytics.
Until recently these have been difficult to do without.
Advertising is a proven business model for high traffic websites
and analytics are critical to understanding your site and users.
However, the internet has responded to users demand for increased privacy by providing privacy-aware services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="privacy-oriented-services-that-eliminate-the-requirement-of-cookie-banners"&gt;Privacy-oriented services that eliminate the requirement of cookie banners&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to analytics, the internet has seen a host of alternatives to industry giant Google Analytics come to market.
They include &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/web-analytics/"&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://usefathom.com"&gt;Fathom&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://plausible.io/"&gt;Plausible&lt;/a&gt; and more.
These either don't set cookies at all or can easily be configured not to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a solution for internet advertising that doesn't trigger cookie banners or violate user privacy has been a larger challenge.
Some ad tech companies are working hard to keep tracking and targeting users without cookies.
This may meet the letter of the law, but definitely violates its intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the many reasons we built EthicalAds.
Our &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertising-vision/"&gt;vision for advertising&lt;/a&gt; is that ads can work well without tracking users.
Instead of setting advertising cookies and learning from users' browsing history,
we focus by advertising only to developers and target ads based on content alone.
And &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/04/ethical-advertising-works/"&gt;this approach works&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're tired of seeing a cookie banner on your site,
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/publishers/"&gt;join EthicalAds&lt;/a&gt; and ditch those annoying banners!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Greg Muscarella for the inspiration and feedback on this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="cookies"></category></entry><entry><title>EthicalAds Newsletter - January 2021</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2021/02/ethicalads-newsletter-january-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-08T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2021-02-08:/blog/2021/02/ethicalads-newsletter-january-2021/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="january-advertising-stats"&gt;January advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, we returned to growth as expected from a slow holiday season.
While the year always …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="january-advertising-stats"&gt;January advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, we returned to growth as expected from a slow holiday season.
While the year always starts a little slow, January started with a lot of advertiser interest and publishers
interested in making money with ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 2021:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We generated &lt;strong&gt;$10,566.78&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers, a 12% increase from December and 5% increase from November, our previous peak.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;103 publishers&lt;/strong&gt; on our network with a paid ad impression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;6,095,608&lt;/strong&gt; paid ad views across the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the Docs, our own publisher, generated &lt;strong&gt;$16,381.53&lt;/strong&gt; on 6,929,551 paid ad impressions. Of our reported metrics, this was the only one down slightly and it was due to a few large advertisers balancing their spend between Read the Docs and our larger ad network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For February, we are expecting another record breaking month in terms of daily traffic, daily revenue, and ads served.
It may not be as high as January in total (it'll be very close) but that's simply due to the number of days in the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-features"&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the major features we added in the last month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On our ad client, we built a feature that allows ads to be displayed in light-mode or dark-mode
  based on the user's preferences if the publisher displaying the ad also supports this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On our ad server, we added a number of quality of life improvements,
  including automating some advertiser setup and fixing some minor data consistency bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In our infrastructure, we started archiving old, raw data on ad impressions
  (remember, we &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertising-vision/"&gt;do not track user personal data&lt;/a&gt;)
  to keep our transactional database small and fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On our website, we put up a job opening which we'll talk about in the next section.
  We also launched some more advertiser and publisher testimonials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see our latest updates in our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-server.readthedocs.io/en/latest/developer/changelog.html"&gt;ethical-ad-server changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="growing-our-team"&gt;Growing our team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We posted a new part-time &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/jobs/account-manager-part-time/"&gt;job opening&lt;/a&gt;
and we're hoping to bring somebody on to help manage advertiser and publisher relationships.
The job is going to be heavy on customer service but has some
light sales and marketing involved too.
This person will have a lot of impact on how EthicalAds continues to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This person will work directly with me (David) and with Eric
to make sure our publishers are getting as much money as they can
while our advertisers are getting the best results we can deliver.
We pride ourselves on the high level of service we provide,
and working closely with both publishers and advertisers helps to get great results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this role sounds interesting to you,
please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@ethicalads.io?subject=Ads%20account%20manager%20role"&gt;get in touch with any questions&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/jobs/account-manager-part-time/"&gt;apply&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, Read the Docs is hiring a &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/job-frontend/"&gt;frontend developer&lt;/a&gt;
and a &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/job-devrel/"&gt;developer advocate with documentation skills&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tricky-bits"&gt;Tricky bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we mentioned in December, hiring and onboarding new team members are hard work and require a lot of time to do well.
Now that we've started getting applications, we expect that this will take some time
but the end result will hopefully be faster responses to our advertisers and publishers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiring new people really can't come soon enough.
Between the the time spent on hiring (which is very important to get right),
time spent on working on &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/czi-grant-announcement/"&gt;Read the Docs' CZI grant&lt;/a&gt;,
and some upcoming infrastructure changes at Read the Docs,
we're all feeling spread a bit thin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-features"&gt;Upcoming features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major features in our upcoming roadmap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want to give both advertisers and publishers high level data right in their dashboard when they first login.
  These are stats like exactly how much advertising money they've spent or earned this month
  and how this month compares with last month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're hoping to expand our advertising logic to take into account price when selecting ads.
  One advantage of this would allow us to have lower priority advertisers who buy ads at a lower rate
  but don't receive guarantees of inventory. This is helpful to make sure publishers are always showing paid ads
  while letting us balance our inventory.
  In January, we did start pitching this advertisers but haven't sold it or completed building it yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We started exploring customized ad placements on single high-value publishers.
  This is different from our traditional ad offering which shows ads across our network
  and instead focuses on buying most or all inventory for a single publisher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for being along with us on this journey to build an ethical ad network.
Please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@ethicalads.io"&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt; if you have any ideas or feedback on our product or roadmap,
we always love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>EthicalAds Newsletter - December 2020</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2021/01/ethicalads-newsletter-december-2020/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-12T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2021-01-12:/blog/2021/01/ethicalads-newsletter-december-2020/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="december-advertising-stats"&gt;December advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;December was a slightly down month here at EthicalAds from our record-breaking November.
Considering the major holidays …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="december-advertising-stats"&gt;December advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;December was a slightly down month here at EthicalAds from our record-breaking November.
Considering the major holidays, I'll still call that a win.
The bulk of our advertising is shown during business hours and there were a lot fewer business hours in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2020:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We generated &lt;strong&gt;$9,373.04&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers, a 7% decrease from November.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;89 publishers&lt;/strong&gt; on our network with a paid ad impression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;5,227,541&lt;/strong&gt; paid ad views across the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/12/ethicalads-newsletter-november-2020/"&gt;November&lt;/a&gt;, we mentioned we were holding out hope of a December increase
while mentioning that it is a historically down month for advertising.
We got pretty close, but weren't quite able to get there.
For January, in spite of the New Years holiday which results in a few days of lower traffic,
we're expecting a return to growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's amazing to look back and realize that while we've been sustaining Read the Docs with advertising for a few years now,
our wider EthicalAds network just started in July and we've been going for only six months.
In just those six months, we've grown from nothing and generated &lt;strong&gt;$42,239&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="read-the-docs-advertising-stats"&gt;Read the Docs advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2021, we wanted to begin to also report Read the Docs' advertising stats just like we're doing for the ad network.
We've reported these numbers previously in yearly &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/read-the-docs-2019-stats/"&gt;Read the Docs stats posts&lt;/a&gt;
but not on a monthly basis like we are for EthicalAds.
We will continue to break out third-party publishers just as we have been so stats will continue to be comparable month over month.
For Read the Docs in December, we achieved &lt;strong&gt;$17,656.37&lt;/strong&gt; in advertising revenue on &lt;strong&gt;8,575,795&lt;/strong&gt; paid ad views.
Our goal here is to treat our own publisher, Read the Docs, as just a regular publisher as far as the ad network is concerned.
From a company perspective, we will be separating them out in terms of accounting and budget as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-features"&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big things we added last month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We broke out our headlines and calls to action in our ads.
  This allows publishers with custom integrations to style them differently and gives advertisers
  a convenient way to show which content should be called out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added some new reporting for advertisers to break down their performance by geography and by publisher.
  We expect that as advertisers analyze this data we are going to get requests to advertise only on specific publishers
  or on more limited geographic subsets. We are still working out exactly how to sell that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We rolled out some testimonials from advertisers and publishers on this site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We also delivered a &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/prospectus/ethicalads-advertiser-prospectus.pdf"&gt;new prospectus for Q1 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
  The largest change was a modest price increase for targeting the US &amp;amp; Canada
  where demand continues to outstrip our supply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see our latest updates in our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-server.readthedocs.io/en/latest/developer/changelog.html"&gt;ethical-ad-server changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="growing-our-team"&gt;Growing our team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month we mentioned that we'd be hoping to expand our team and that's going to start this month.
Both the Read the Docs team and the ads team are going to expand
and job postings will be up by the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For advertising, we are looking to bring on a part-time person
to help manage advertiser and publisher relationships.
At the beginning, this role will involve some customer service along with some light sales and marketing,
but the role could specialize in either direction as we continue to grow.
As I mentioned, this will start as a part-time role but we hope it will become a full-time role
by the second half of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This person will work directly with me (David) and with Eric
to make sure our publishers are getting as much money as they can
while our advertisers are getting the best results we can deliver.
Unlike many SaaS businesses, advertising is a little higher touch,
and working closely with both publishers and advertisers helps to get great results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this role sounds interesting to you, please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@ethicalads.io?subject=Ads%20relationship%20manager%20role"&gt;let us know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tricky-bits"&gt;Tricky bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both hiring and afterward onboarding new team members are hard work and require a lot of time to do well.
We expect that this will take some time but the end result will hopefully be faster responses
to our advertisers and publishers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning in 2021, we want to treat Read the Docs as simply another publisher
and this means separating out the budget and accounting of each.
To get specific, we'll be attributing 70% of ad revenue on Read the Docs to Read the Docs itself
and count the other 30% of the revenue toward the EthicalAds network just as we do with third-party publishers.
This will let us better allocate resources to grow both sides of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another upcoming challenge in the next month is an engineering challenge around how we save data for long term archival.
While we &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertising-vision/"&gt;explicitly do not track user personal data&lt;/a&gt;,
we still end up storing a large amount of data on ad impressions
in case we get issues with fraud or merely a billing dispute.
This data is close to exceeding what's reasonable to store in our transactional database and we'll need to move
into a system that can scale up a lot but it won't have real-time requirements.
While this is a fairly well-understood OLTP/OLAP kind of problem,
adding new infrastructure to our reporting is never easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-features"&gt;Upcoming features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major features in our upcoming roadmap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want to give both advertisers and publishers high level data right in their dashboard when they first login.
  These are stats like exactly how much advertising money they've spent or earned this month
  and how this month compares with last month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're hoping to expand our advertising logic to take into account price when selecting ads.
  This will allow us to assure maximum revenue for a publisher,
  but we don't want to always show a single ad on that site, either.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hope to do a beta test of a sponsorship program with a publisher,
  which is an extension of the ad network to allow for specific and customized placements on high-value publishers.
  If you're get advertisers asking you directly how to advertise on your site,
  please let us know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for being along with us on this journey to build an ethical ad network.
Please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@ethicalads.io"&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt; if you have any ideas or feedback on our product or roadmap,
we always love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>EthicalAds Newsletter - November 2020</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/12/ethicalads-newsletter-november-2020/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Eric Holscher</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2020-12-03:/blog/2020/12/ethicalads-newsletter-november-2020/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="november-advertising-stats"&gt;November advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November was a record-breaking month here at EthicalAds.
Even though we had a major US holiday and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="november-advertising-stats"&gt;November advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November was a record-breaking month here at EthicalAds.
Even though we had a major US holiday and only 30 days,
we were able to increase publisher revenue by over 30% this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major driver of increased revenue was being added to the Acceptable Ads list in mid-November.
We estimate this will increase publisher revenue by 10-15%,
which explains a lot of the increase in publisher revenue.
The other major driver of revenue is adding additional publishers to the network,
which we continue to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 2020:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We generated &lt;strong&gt;$10,059.39&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers, breaking $10,000 for the first time!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;79 publishers&lt;/strong&gt; on our network with a paid ad impression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;5,484,006&lt;/strong&gt; paid ad views across the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are excited that all of our core metrics increased this month.
We hope they will continue to increase in December,
but December is historically a low traffic month because there are more global holidays,
so we'll have to wait to find out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-features"&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big things we added this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were approved for the Acceptable Ads program, which required changes to both our server and client to track traffic we can attribute to the program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added reporting for Advertisers to see what Countries and Publishers their ads are showing on the most.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added keyword reporting for Publishers. This allows them to see the performance of the various keywords they are sending on incoming traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We improved our payout workflow, which is part of the work required to lower our payout limit of $50.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added backend support for Fill Rate tracking. This allows us to understand more about how ads are being filled across keywords, geos, and publishers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see our latest updates in our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-server.readthedocs.io/en/latest/developer/changelog.html"&gt;ethical-ad-server changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tricky-bits"&gt;Tricky bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month has felt like the ad network has really hit its stride.
The inclusion of EthicalAds on the Acceptable Ads program is a major benefit,
and has removed our longest-running difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of launching the ad network,
we have had 2 members of the team (Eric &amp;amp; David) fully focused on advertising.
As we look to grow the network,
we are hoping to expand our team by at least one person in the near future.
We have started thinking about a job description for the person we hope to bring on.
Hiring is always a challenge,
but we're excited about having growth to be able to think about supporting an additional team member.
The role we're imagining is an part-time account executive,
but someone who is interested in growing into a larger full-time business role over time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of this transition,
our team member Eric will be scaling back his involvement on advertising from close to 100% of time to 50%.
This will allow us to bring on an additional team member without hurting our budget too much,
until we can fully support having a team of 3 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have also almost fully completed the separation of Read the Docs and EthicalAds.
In January 2021,
we are planning to fully separate the businesses in terms of our accounting and budget.
This will be the end result of the transition of Read the Docs to being a normal Publisher on EthicalAds.
It will likely take us a few months to fully work through this transition,
but it will allow us to grow advertising more quickly as we see growth in the ad network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-features"&gt;Upcoming features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major features in our upcoming roadmap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're still hoping to adapt our ad format to &lt;a href="https://github.com/readthedocs/ethical-ad-server/issues/152"&gt;break out a headline and a call to action&lt;/a&gt;. This will standardize our ad display, along with making sure that all our advertisers have ads that work across multiple formats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want to give advertisers a way to change the flight targeting of their advertisements. Changing targeting generally changes the pricing, so this will require the dashboard knowing more about pricing for different targeting options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're hoping to expand our advertising logic to take into account price when selecting ads. This will allow us to assure maximum revenue for a publisher, but we don't want to always show a single ad on that site, either. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hope to do a beta test of a sponsorship program with a publisher, which is an extension of the ad network to allow for specific placements on high-value publishers. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for being along with us on this journey to build an ethical ad network.
Please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@ethicalads.io"&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt; if you have any ideas or feedback on our product or roadmap,
we always love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>EthicalAds Newsletter - October 2020</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/11/ethicalads-newsletter-october-2020/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-11-02T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Eric Holscher</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2020-11-02:/blog/2020/11/ethicalads-newsletter-october-2020/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="advertising-stats"&gt;Advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October was another productive month on our side.
We continue to onboard new publishers and advertisers.
Growing the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="advertising-stats"&gt;Advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October was another productive month on our side.
We continue to onboard new publishers and advertisers.
Growing the network each month feels great,
and we're always looking for more folks to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of development,
we've been focusing a lot on performance and reporting improvements.
This work makes sure ads load fast, which improves the user experience.
The additional reporting improvements we've made should help publishers understand the ads running on their site in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of stats, in October 2020:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We generated &lt;strong&gt;$7,580.43&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;72 publishers&lt;/strong&gt; on our network with a paid ad impression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;4,571,606&lt;/strong&gt; paid ad views across the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, we actually had fewer ad views this month, mostly because one of larger publishers had some integration issues.
We were able to increase revenue though with fewer ads,
which shows that our pricing increases are starting to take effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-features"&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big things we added this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have started adding &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/publishers/readthedocs/"&gt;testimonials&lt;/a&gt; to our website from our publishers and advertisers. We only have a couple completed, but will be adding more in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have added reporting for publishers that show Geo and Advertiser breakdowns. These are in beta and will be enabled for everyone this week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have added &lt;a href="https://github.com/readthedocs/ethical-ad-client/pull/29/"&gt;viewport tracking&lt;/a&gt; to our ad client. This is a backstop to our Publisher Policy, confirming that ads are actually viewed for billing purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We migrated our hosting infrastructure from a Docker-based solution to a VM-based solution. This brought a 3x improvement to our average server response latency, which is now 45ms on average and 75ms at the 99th percentile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As part of this server migration we have built the capability to do &lt;a href="https://github.com/readthedocs/ethical-ad-server/pull/260/files"&gt;periodic report generation&lt;/a&gt;. We're currently updating the Geo reports each hour, but will tweak this over time as we figure out what the best options here are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We also updated our ad integration on Read the Docs to use the standard ethical-ad-client. This is one of the last steps of making Read the Docs "just another publisher" and not be special. As part of this, we removed legacy ad types, and now all ads are the same image+text or image-only ads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see our latest updates in our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-server.readthedocs.io/en/latest/developer/changelog.html"&gt;ethical-ad-server changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tricky-bits"&gt;Tricky bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels like we've managed to address most of our existing issues. Our server performance has been a nagging issue since launched, and it's very excited to have fixed it and seen quite impressive gains. Having additional infrastructure to handle periodic reporting is also another major thing we needed to do, so that we can add more reporting without impacting advertising performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a signed contract with the Acceptable Ads program, which is a major milestone. We expect this change to roll out early in November, which we forecast will bring an increase of 15% more ads shown. This will increase our publishers revenue and removes a large structural barrier that we faced to competing with other advertising networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our ongoing worries is about balancing supply and demand on the network. Especially with keyword targeting, it can be hard to maintain fill rates across our publisher network while also fully filling campaigns for our advertisers. We expect this will continue to be a difficult task forever, but we're slowly starting to understand how to balance this tension. We're also working to manage expectations on both sides, knowing that forecasting web traffic isn't an exact science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-features"&gt;Upcoming features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our upcoming roadmap has a few major tasks on it this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're planning to adapt our ad format to &lt;a href="https://github.com/readthedocs/ethical-ad-server/issues/152"&gt;break out a headline and a call to action&lt;/a&gt;. This will standardize our ad display, along with making sure that all our advertisers have ads that work across multiple formats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're working on a Publisher Prospectus, which is similar to our &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/prospectus/ethicalads-advertiser-prospectus.pdf"&gt;advertiser prospectus&lt;/a&gt; -- a single place to understand what being a publisher looks like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We didn't get to it last month, but we want additional publisher &amp;amp; advertiser landing pages. We hope to build topic-specific pages to share more information for specific audiences on these pages, to go along with our testimonials. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We started conversations about trademarking EthicalAds, but haven't applied for it yet. This process will take 4-6 months, but we do want to make sure we've gotten it started.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We plan to take our expanded publisher reports and add similar improvements to our advertising reports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other small tasks we'll continue to work on, along with lots of email :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for following along on our journey, and we're excited to continue to build something we can all be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>EthicalAds Newsletter - September 2020</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/10/ethicalads-newsletter-september-2020/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Eric Holscher</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2020-10-06:/blog/2020/10/ethicalads-newsletter-september-2020/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="advertising-stats"&gt;Advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September was a solid month of growth for our EthicalAds Network.
We have continued to onboard additional publishers …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2 id="advertising-stats"&gt;Advertising stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September was a solid month of growth for our EthicalAds Network.
We have continued to onboard additional publishers and expand our list of advertisers.
We have also released our &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/prospectus/ethicalads-advertiser-prospectus.pdf"&gt;Q4 advertiser prospectus&lt;/a&gt; which has raised some of our prices given the increased interest we're seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increase in prices should start showing up throughout the month of September for our publishers.
Publisher revenue is the thing we care most about,
and we're happy to report that it grew &lt;strong&gt;32%&lt;/strong&gt; this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2020:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We generated &lt;strong&gt;$6,966.84&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers -- so close to $7k!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;65 publishers&lt;/strong&gt; on our network with a paid ad impression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;4,829,240&lt;/strong&gt; paid ad views across the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-features"&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continued to add more features for publishers and advertisers to understand what is happening on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big things we added this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/"&gt;new website&lt;/a&gt; with an updated design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We combined our Read the Docs &amp;amp; EthicalAds landing pages and prospectus, so we only have a single source of that information now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/prospectus/ethicalads-advertiser-prospectus.pdf"&gt;Q4 advertiser prospectus&lt;/a&gt; with updated topics and pricing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ad client support for &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-client.readthedocs.io/en/latest/#ad-placement-reporting"&gt;placement reporting&lt;/a&gt; which allows seeing reports for specific placements on your site (eg. an ad on a list screen vs. a detail screen)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ad client support for &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-client.readthedocs.io/en/latest/#page-specific-keywords"&gt;per-page keywords&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see our latest updates in our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-server.readthedocs.io/en/latest/developer/changelog.html"&gt;ethical-ad-server changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tricky-bits"&gt;Tricky bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our current top priority continues to be getting publishers more revenue. As part of that mission we have raised prices on some of our more popular targeting options for Q4, and are expanding the topics we are targeting to better reflect out publishers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to have issues with ad blocking. We have had a good call with the Acceptable Ads team, and are hopeful that we will be added to the approved list in October. That will raise most of our publishers revenues by an estimated 15%, which would be huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other major thing we continue to struggle with is just the amount of work we need to do. Spinning up an entirely new ad network and brand requires a lot of various tasks, and we only have 2 people working on it mostly full-time. We are in discussion in Q4 about doing some kind of hiring, either contract or part-time with the revenue we're seeing from the ad network. We generally try to be conservative in our hiring, so it might get pushed back to next year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-features"&gt;Upcoming features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We managed to achieve 3 of the 5 &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/09/ethicalads-newsletter-august-2020/#upcoming-features"&gt;features we wanted from last month&lt;/a&gt;.
We are still planning to write more blog content and ship a publisher prospectus, but they were pushed back by more pressing work this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, our roadmap this month includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A number of reporting improvements for both advertisers and publishers, to better understand their traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adapt Read the Docs to use our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-client.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;official ad client&lt;/a&gt; instead of the custom integration we have now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trademark "Ethical Ads", now that we are using it as a brand. We hope we will be able to get it, otherwise we might need to consider a re-brand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additional publisher &amp;amp; advertiser landing pages. We hope to build topic-specific pages to share more information for specific audiences on these pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get testimonials from our users. We have now been serving network ads for close to 3 months, so we should have some happy customers now :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the big roadmap items for us this next month, but we always have additional tasks each month like replying to email and processing payouts.
We'll continue working diligently to bring the best ad network that we can to the developer community,
and we're glad you're with us for the journey.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>EthicalAds Newsletter - August 2020</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/09/ethicalads-newsletter-august-2020/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Eric Holscher</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2020-09-03:/blog/2020/09/ethicalads-newsletter-august-2020/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're excited to share you with our first newsletter,
where we'll share updates about our progress.
Inspired by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/coderberry"&gt;Eric Berry …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're excited to share you with our first newsletter,
where we'll share updates about our progress.
Inspired by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/coderberry"&gt;Eric Berry&lt;/a&gt; and the CodeFund team,
we'll also share our struggles and challenges.
We believe strongly that being transparent and ethical go hand in hand,
and will strive to share as much as we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="advertising-stats"&gt;Advertising Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;August is the first full month that we've served ads on our EthicalAds network.
We're excited to already be supporting so many publishers.
Making sure developers are paid for their work is a huge part of our mission,
and revenue paid out is our most important stat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We generated &lt;strong&gt;$5,375.22&lt;/strong&gt; for our publishers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had &lt;strong&gt;50 publishers&lt;/strong&gt; on our network with a paid ad impression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-features"&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're working hard on building new features as we get more feedback from our advertisers and publishers.
It's still early days,
and we really appreciate how understanding everyone has been with any confusion in our processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big things we added this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added an explicit &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/publisher-policy/"&gt;Publisher Policy&lt;/a&gt; to set expectations in our relationship with our publishers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We added an &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertisers/faq/"&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt; to the EthicalAds site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We documented our &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertising-vision/"&gt;Ad Vision&lt;/a&gt; on the website, showing how we're different than other ad networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We improved our fraud detection mechanisms to be smarter about rate limiting ad views and detect when users are using a proxy to view the documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publishers can now store payout setting in the dashboard directly. This improves our workflow for paying out publishers, hopefully making it smoother.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always see the latest code updates in our &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-server.readthedocs.io/en/latest/developer/changelog.html"&gt;changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tricky-bits"&gt;Tricky bits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our current priority is getting publishers more money. We know that we're a little bit below what some other networks are able to pay because of how new we are. We're fully focused on improving this situation, and it has happened for a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our largest issue in August was getting added to the main ad block lists. We're currently working with the team at Eyeo (AdBlock Plus) to get our new ads on the Acceptable Ads list. Ad blocking removed 30% of our total traffic, which was a large impact. Being put on Acceptable Ads &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/05/update-on-ad-blocking-and-acceptable-ads/"&gt;got around 50% of those blocked views back&lt;/a&gt; when it happened to Read the Docs in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two other places we're working to improve this situation: raising our prices and selling more of our inventory. Since we had to scramble to get everything sold when we launched in July, we didn't have time to adjust our prices and do a full sales cycle with our advertisers. The other aspect is that a lot of our APAC inventory is unsold. For some of our publishers, this means 50% of ad views aren't currently being monetized. We generally recommend &lt;a href="https://ethical-ad-client.readthedocs.io/en/latest/#customization"&gt;falling back to other content&lt;/a&gt; in these cases, if that is something you're comfortable doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="upcoming-features"&gt;Upcoming features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a number of new things on our roadmap for September.
We'll try to share our upcoming roadmap,
so folks have an idea of what we're working on this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our large roadmap items are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve our codebase to support multiple placements for one Publisher. This will be useful for sites with multiple placements that want to track performance between them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unify the old advertising pages on Read the Docs with our new EthicalAds ones, making everything a bit clearer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve Publisher onboarding, including sharing more information about expectations in a Publisher prospectus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ship our Q4 prospectus, with some additional improvements around explaining what EthicalAds is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write more blog content around how to market to developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're always open to additional feedback and ideas on our approach,
so feel free to &lt;a href="mailto:ads@readthedocs.org"&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt; directly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="newsletter"></category><category term="community"></category></entry><entry><title>Announcing EthicalAds</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/08/announcing-ethicalads/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Eric Holscher</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2020-08-24:/blog/2020/08/announcing-ethicalads/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're excited to announce the release of EthicalAds,
a privacy-focused ad network for developers.
We think advertising is one of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're excited to announce the release of EthicalAds,
a privacy-focused ad network for developers.
We think advertising is one of the best ways to fund open source development,
and we have first hand experience.
Ethical advertising was first created to make Read the Docs,
our own open source project,
sustainable.
We're now bringing ethical ads to other developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've found that privacy preserving ads are a win for both developers and advertisers.
Advertisers are able to target developers on the sites they frequent without being blocked.
Developers trust our ads because our code is open source, and we're developers ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-background"&gt;The background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethical advertising as a concept was something we &lt;a href="https://www.ericholscher.com/blog/2016/aug/31/funding-oss-marketing-money/#funding-read-the-docs"&gt;originally conceived&lt;/a&gt; for Read the Docs back in 2016.
We were an open source project trying to find sustainability,
and advertising was the answer we knew we needed.
We knew our users cared about privacy,
so we decided to build the most privacy-focused ad solution we could.
We have been working on building a sturdy business around advertising ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we started building this vision,
we were inspired to see CodeFund adopt our ideals and push them forward.
We were sad when we heard CodeFund was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/codefundio/status/1278119643937296384"&gt;shutting down&lt;/a&gt; on July 1 of this year.
We talked with Eric Berry at CodeFund,
deciding to launch our network in beta to provide a smooth transition for the people depending on that money each month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've spent the last month onboarding over 50 publishers.
&lt;strong&gt;Developers have already earned more than $5,000 since we launched&lt;/strong&gt;.
We're excited to officially announce that we're open for additional publishers and advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="our-vision"&gt;Our vision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethical ads respect users while still providing value to advertisers.
The vision is pretty simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don’t track you or sell your data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We only make money showing ads, so our interests are fully aligned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We target ads based on the content of the current page, not your past browsing history&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are as transparent in our business as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We only show high quality ads from companies that are of interest to developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we talked about in our &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ethical-advertising-works/"&gt;2018 blog post&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;ethical advertising works&lt;/strong&gt;.
We're thrilled to be able to bring our vision of advertising to a larger audience,
and help fund open source without compromise.
Our &lt;a href="https://github.com/readthedocs/ethical-ad-server"&gt;entire ad server&lt;/a&gt; is open source,
so you can inspect how we're doing things.
We believe strongly in open source,
and we practice what we preach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="join-us"&gt;Join us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are planning to grow slowly in the near term,
making sure that everything we've built is ready for new demands.
We've already learned a number of lessons in the last month,
and we want to make sure our ads work well for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethical advertising is our vision for the future of internet advertising,
and we hope that you'll join us.
We have space for additional publishers and advertisers,
and look forward to building something meaningful with you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become a &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/publishers/"&gt;publisher&lt;/a&gt; today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become an &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertisers/"&gt;advertiser&lt;/a&gt; today&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow our journey in our &lt;a href="https://ethicalads.us17.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=ca5e74de3ea2867d373058271&amp;amp;id=5746f18bb8"&gt;newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category></entry><entry><title>Advertising update and open sourcing our ad server</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2020/07/advertising-update-and-open-sourcing-our-ad-server/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2020-07-01:/blog/2020/07/advertising-update-and-open-sourcing-our-ad-server/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/advertising-improvements-2020/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a while since our
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/06/ad-funding-at-read-the-docs-and-whats-next-for-ethical-advertising/"&gt;last advertising update …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/advertising-improvements-2020/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a while since our
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/06/ad-funding-at-read-the-docs-and-whats-next-for-ethical-advertising/"&gt;last advertising update&lt;/a&gt;
and it felt like a good time to talk about what's working
with our advertising model and how things are getting better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-advertising-is-working-for-read-the-docs"&gt;How advertising is working for Read the Docs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/read-the-docs-2019-stats/"&gt;2019 stats post&lt;/a&gt;,
we broke out our advertising revenue which was fairly flat
year over year. The way our ad business is structured, our revenue
mostly grows with increases in traffic and Read the Docs is mature
enough that it isn't doubling in size every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, we're pleased with our steady and sustainable growth.
Read the Docs doesn't have any investors putting pressure on us for
short term growth and that has allowed us to invest in our ad business,
commercial hosting, and in our community version for the long term.
We've rolled out a huge number of improvements to all the sides of our
business in the last year and we're happy with the results. Advertising
remains the single largest source of funding for Read the Docs and one
that scales as our costs scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a real world note, Covid-19 had a short term impact on our
advertising revenue with a number of advertisers understandably pulling
back due to uncertainty in funding and the economy in general. While the
world isn't completely back to normal, we have returned some degree of
normalcy and most of these advertisers returned once there was a bit
more clarity in the broader economy and the virus' effect on the tech
industry specifically. Advertising on Read the Docs is now close to
capacity in the US, Canada, and Europe which are our largest advertising
markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="improved-targeting-for-ads"&gt;Improved targeting for ads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advertising on Read the Docs is different from most ad networks out
there. Our ad targeting is based on the content and the reader's
geography rather than personal data about our users. Read the Docs'
authors and readers have told us that privacy is important to them.
That's great because it's important to us too! With that said, there
are great ways to target specific content niches with ads relevant to
those readers without compromising on privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, we chose a few groups of content advertisers can target where
we have enough traffic without the ads being focused on a tiny number of
projects. These niches are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data science and machine learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frontend web development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backend web development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DevOps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical writing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested this improved content targeting with a select group of
advertisers and the results were great. In some cases we saw click
through rates more than double. Whether the ad is to hire a developer or
to promote a service, we always want to deliver ads that are most
relevant to the documentation being served. This results in better value
to our advertisers while still respecting the privacy of our readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would your company like to get in front of more developers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell your &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertisers/"&gt;marketing or recruiting team&lt;/a&gt; about Read the Docs and show
them how they can reach over 7 million developers who Read the Docs each
month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="open-sourcing-our-ad-server"&gt;Open sourcing our ad server&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing we've wanted to do for a long time is open source the code we
use to run advertising at Read the Docs. While there's always a bit of
an incentive to keep advertising code closed so it can't be abused, our
hope is that the trust we're building with the ethical ads model can be
used by others who want to run their own ethical advertising. Read the
Docs is an open source company and it's nice to have all our code out
there. We call it the ethical ad server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ethical ad server is built to handle the kind of load Read the Docs
itself receives -- over a million hits per day -- and it delivers
advertising based only on content and geographic targeting rather than
building up user profiles from personal information. It's built from
the ground up with user privacy in mind. We're excited to share it with
you so please &lt;a href="https://github.com/readthedocs/ethical-ad-server"&gt;check out the code on
GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as we're constantly delivering improvements to Read the Docs
itself for our readers and project maintainers, we also strive to give a
better experience and better results to the companies who trust Read the
Docs as a marketing channel. I want to thank all our advertisers who
believe in our approach and continue to support us and stay tuned to
this space for more great features in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ethical ad network is just about ready for launch and we're
actively looking for projects to beta test the network. If you run a
developer focused website and you're looking for a way to earn money
without selling out your visitors' privacy, please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@readthedocs.org?subject=Ethical%20Ad%20Network%20beta"&gt;get in
touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="opensource"></category><category term="readthedocs"></category></entry><entry><title>Ad Funding at Read the Docs and What's Next for Ethical Advertising</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/06/ad-funding-at-read-the-docs-and-whats-next-for-ethical-advertising/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2019-06-11:/blog/2019/06/ad-funding-at-read-the-docs-and-whats-next-for-ethical-advertising/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ad-funding-read-the-docs-whats-next/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been three years since we first launched …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ad-funding-read-the-docs-whats-next/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been three years since we first launched
&lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ads-on-read-the-docs/"&gt;ads on Read the Docs&lt;/a&gt;
and while we gave a limited update in our
&lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/read-the-docs-2018-stats/"&gt;2018 stats&lt;/a&gt;,
we figured it was time to give an update on ethical advertising and how
it is working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="advertising-without-tracking"&gt;Advertising without tracking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our ethical advertising model is still going strong.&lt;/strong&gt; We proved that
it is possible to build a business model on top of advertising without
resorting to user tracking. Unlike most other ad-supported sites, we
show advertising based on the context of the page, not by creating
behavoral profiles of large numbers of individual users. If you are
browsing documentation for a Python project, you might see a relevant ad
about Python. It's that simple and it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a slow start to the year, we expect to earn about $75,000 from
advertising in Q2. This brings our advertising revenue back to the level
before our ads were
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/05/ads-and-ad-blockers/"&gt;added to major ad blocking lists&lt;/a&gt; last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we do earn money from other sources such as our &lt;a href="https://readthedocs.com"&gt;commercial
offering&lt;/a&gt;, advertising continues to be our
largest source of revenue and has allowed us to expand our team to five
full-time people. Compared with three years ago when we were scraping
along with very little money, our community issue tracker and support
requests receive prompt responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="progress"&gt;Progress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've made great progress on advertising over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We survived a major hit to revenue from ad blocking without
    resorting to cat and mouse games of changing ad layouts and APIs to
    avoid ad blockers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://docs.readthedocs.io/page/advertising/ethical-advertising.html#community-ads"&gt;community ads
    program&lt;/a&gt;
    has been significantly expanded. We are actively running free
    community advertising promoting over ten open source projects and
    conferences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While we never tracked users with advertising, we put in place
    stricter &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/do-not-track/"&gt;Do Not Track&lt;/a&gt;
    privacy protections. We continue to believe that
    advertising can be well targeted without tracking users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We launched an advertising vertical to let companies
    &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/01/lessons-from-and-for-hiring-managers/"&gt;promote their open jobs&lt;/a&gt; to developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our advertising revenue share program tripled in size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ethical advertising approach, with no user tracking, has been key to
our sustainability and has allowed Read the Docs to continue to build
new features and give back to our community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="whats-next"&gt;What's next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have some really interesting developments coming regarding ethical
advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are looking to add a few more projects to our ad &lt;strong&gt;revenue share
program&lt;/strong&gt; and help more projects reach sustainability with an ethical
advertising approach. If your project on Read the Docs does 100k+
pageviews per month and you are interested in exploring a new revenue
stream, please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@readthedocs.org?subject=Ethical%20Ads%20revenue%20share"&gt;let us
know&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are testing a &lt;strong&gt;new text-only ad format&lt;/strong&gt; which we will detail in a
future post. Text-only ads are something we've wanted for a while
because we believe they are less intrusive to readers but easy for
advertisers to experiment with multiple variations. So far the results
have been very promising and we are planning to roll this out more
widely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;strong&gt;ethical ad network&lt;/strong&gt; is getting closer to launch. It's a shame,
but there's a critical lack of funding for open source projects that
form the building blocks of some extremely valuable software. We believe
that advertising can fill some of that gap and Read the Docs can help by
sharing some of the lessons we've learned building our own advertising.
If you know a site that might be interested in being a beta tester of a
pro-privacy ad network built specifically to help fund open source,
please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@readthedocs.org?subject=Ethical%20Ad%20Network%20beta"&gt;get in
touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thanks"&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advertisers always have a choice where to direct their marketing spend
and for many of them it would have been simpler to just go with the
usual behemoth advertising platforms rather than advertising with a
niche site like Read the Docs. I want to thank all our advertisers who
believe in our approach and continue to support us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="readthedocs"></category></entry><entry><title>Tips for Getting a Developer Interview</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/02/tips-for-getting-a-developer-interview/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2019-02-13:/blog/2019/02/tips-for-getting-a-developer-interview/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/tips-for-getting-a-developer-interview/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last month, the Read the Docs team …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/tips-for-getting-a-developer-interview/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last month, the Read the Docs team conducted 30-40 customer
development interviews with hiring managers and recruiters at companies
ranging from 5-person companies to the biggest names in tech. We wanted
to learn more about hiring processes at various companies with the
ultimate goal of building &lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertisers/hiring/"&gt;a product to help companies find
developers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time, we covered some
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/01/lessons-from-and-for-hiring-managers/"&gt;tips for hiring managers&lt;/a&gt;
based on what companies told us they were doing. This time,
we put together &lt;strong&gt;tips for candidates looking for their next job&lt;/strong&gt; based
on insights we heard from hiring managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than covering how to crack developer interviews or how to gain
the necessary technical skills, these tips will focus on getting your
foot in the door. Specifically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making your application stand out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving your application response rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting to the interview process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-applying-go-deep-not-wide"&gt;When applying, go deep not wide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I don't want candidates who drive by job sites and pepper every job
they find"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a candidate, there is a temptation to play the numbers game and apply
to as many jobs as possible. Many jobs sites make it easy to apply to
many jobs quickly and this gives you that feeling that your job search
is progressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Based on what hiring managers told us, playing the numbers game isn't
the best approach.&lt;/strong&gt; While it is a bit of a job-seekers market,
especially for more senior talent, companies are looking people who want
to work for their company and who believe in their mission. Hiring
managers told us they want applicants who "think about the company,
then check for opportunities".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2019-facebook-job-opening.png" class="mw-100" alt="Facebook job posting with almost 300 applications in 2 weeks on just one of the job sites where this is posted."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="spend-a-little-more-time-on-your-application"&gt;Spend a little more time on your application&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it takes longer to apply to a job post that requires a cover
letter or requires answers to a few questions, those are great ways to
have your application stand out relative to other applicants. You don't
want your resume to get lost in a stack of hundreds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we mentioned
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/01/lessons-from-and-for-hiring-managers/"&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt;,
quite a few hiring managers we talked to started requiring
a cover letter or even just a couple questions that are unique to the
company in order to make their job filtering candidates easier and get
candidates who want to work there not those who just want a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the companies we talked to said when they post a job they got tons
of applicants, but that high quality, qualified applicants were still in
short supply. When 200 people apply to a job but only 20 are willing to
do a cover letter, a hiring manager can spend a lot more time per
candidate with the smaller pool. One hiring manager told us explicitly
"fewer resumes is better because there's less noise".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I know I said getting a developer job isn't a numbers game, this
doesn't strictly mean you can use these techniques to apply to 2-3 jobs
and you'll get hired. Sometimes by the time you apply, somebody is
already in the final stages of getting hired. The position may not
&lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; be open anymore. Don't get discouraged in your job search.
&lt;strong&gt;Finding the right match can take time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2019-duckduckgo-application-questions.png" class="mw-100" alt="Here's some of the questions from the DuckDuckGo application process.This is your place to stand out! DuckDuckGo was **not** one of the companies we interviewed."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="make-yourself-a-referral-use-your-network"&gt;Make yourself a referral: use your network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiring managers universally told us their top recruiting channel is
referrals from existing employees. As a candidate, use this knowledge to
your advantage and &lt;strong&gt;make yourself into a referral hire&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did you see an acquaintance on social media post about job openings
    at their company?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does a friend or a friend of friend work at the company?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have a first connection (or a very good 2nd connection) on
    LinkedIn who works there?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all of these cases, you should contact that person before applying.
Even if the person you know isn't on the hiring team, your contact
might be able to put you in touch with the right person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Most [senior] people go through their network"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a mid-level to senior candidate with 7+ years of experience, this is
even more important based on our interviews. At that stage of your
career, &lt;strong&gt;hiring managers we talked to expect a high quality candidate
to do due diligence&lt;/strong&gt; on the company and team to make sure it's a
mutual fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the exact route you take here, getting in touch with the
right people to learn more about the team, the tech stack, and the
company makes it clear that you're very interested. You're far more
likely to get a response, move on to the interview process, and
ultimately get hired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="establishing-contact-with-companies"&gt;Establishing contact with companies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning yourself into a referral is easier for a senior candidate. But
what if this is your first or second job or don't know anybody at the
company?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After referral candidates, &lt;strong&gt;the next best hiring channel in our
interviews was local meetups and engaging the local community&lt;/strong&gt;. Both
startups and established companies -- especially when they are actively
hiring -- use meetups to find talent. If you're able to meet the hiring
manager in person or establish some sort of connection, in my
experience, this raises your chances significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our interviews, another channel that mid-size and larger companies we
talked to used to recruit was to rely on their presense at conferences.
For many companies, recruiting was the primary motivator to sponsor a
conference and have a booth. As a candidate, talking to the engineers at
the booth and showing interest can ensure that your application doesn't
get lost among all the applicants they get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a smaller company, it's frequently possible to figure out exactly
who the hiring manager is from some combination of the website, hiring
posts, and LinkedIn. This is a great way to make a valuable connection
and make sure the role is a good fit. Contacting the hiring manager cold
requires a bit of finesse so make sure to be respectful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Places like the monthly HackerNews Who's Hiring thread are fantastic
because they allow direct interaction with the hiring manager and many
companies list a person's direct email to inquire about a position,
learn more directly from the source, and show you're interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2019-hiring-manager-phrases.png" class="mw-100" alt="Here's some of the phrases we heard from hiring managers in
interviews."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By spending a bit more time on your application, establishing contact
with the company, and asking good questions about the work and team, you
are showing your intent and interest in the company.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to make sure the hiring manager or recruiter understands that
you're a serious candidate and you want to work there on their team.
Using these methods will improve your response rate and &lt;strong&gt;help you get
the interview&lt;/strong&gt;. By doing a one-click apply on a job site, this is
completely lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thanks"&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I'd like to thank all the hiring managers who took the time to
talk to us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="hiring"></category><category term="readthedocs"></category></entry><entry><title>Lessons From and For Hiring Managers</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/01/lessons-from-and-for-hiring-managers/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-30T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-30T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2019-01-30:/blog/2019/01/lessons-from-and-for-hiring-managers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/lessons-from-hiring-manager-interviews/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last four weeks, the Read the Docs …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/lessons-from-hiring-manager-interviews/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last four weeks, the Read the Docs team did dozens of customer
development interviews with engineering hiring managers. We wanted to
learn more about hiring processes at various companies with the ultimate
goal of building a product to help companies find developers. We talked
to people looking for talent at five person companies all the way up to
the biggest names in tech. In this post, I am going to cover some of the
common things we heard from hiring managers and &lt;strong&gt;share some ways for
hiring managers to improve their company's process&lt;/strong&gt;. In our
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/02/tips-for-getting-a-developer-interview/"&gt;next post in this series&lt;/a&gt;,
I will have some actionable tips for job seekers based on
the same interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is a long post, I figured I'd share some of the key
takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a strategy for getting more referrals&lt;/strong&gt; whether that is
    actively asking employees or having an overly generous referral
    bonus. Referrals are probably your top source of candidates so
    figuring out how to get more will save you time and money in the
    end. Then do the same for your other best recruiting channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reach passive candidates&lt;/strong&gt;. There are a lot more passive
    candidates than active ones so have a plan to reach them. Great
    developers (especially senior ones) probably aren't actively
    looking for a new job and it's a job-seekers market. Even if
    somebody isn't considering a new job at all, the next time they do,
    you want them to think of your company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recruiting for diversity is a focus&lt;/strong&gt; for hiring managers. Put
    together a concrete plan for getting more diverse candidates and
    meeting your diversity goals. Engaging with local developer
    communities and nonprofits and encouraging referrals worked well for
    companies we talked to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get more signal in your application process&lt;/strong&gt; by adding a step
    such as a cover letter, quiz, or simply add a couple questions folks
    have to answer. Making candidates spend even one extra minute on
    their application can save you hours filtering resumes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-is-read-the-docs-tackling-hiring-hasnt-that-been-done"&gt;Why is Read the Docs tackling hiring? Hasn't that been done?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we didn't initially think about Read the Docs ads for recruiting,
based on some
unexpected past successes](hiring-developers-with-readthedocs.md),
we decided to position promoted jobs as one of our main
verticals within our advertising. Rather than dash forward and create a
product, however, we started by just talking to hiring managers to
understand the hiring process better so we can best meet their needs
with something we create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the questions we asked in our interviews was how long it took to
hire their most recent developer? Specifically, we asked hiring managers
to consider how much time they and their team spent sourcing candidates,
filtering resumes, preparing for and doing phone and onsite interviews,
and anything else. Internal recruiters' time is valuable too, but we
figured the hiring manager would probably underestimate how much time
the recruiter spent since they didn't directly observe it. While
answers were all over the place, the range with the most overlap was
&lt;strong&gt;50-100 hours of engineering time to make a hire&lt;/strong&gt;. No huge revelation
here, but companies make a massive investment in hiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my days being an interviewer at Qualcomm and Amazon as well as a
smaller startup, I'd say fifty hours is on the low side for big company
but about right for a smaller company. When something costs 50+
engineering hours to do, any improvement is worth a lot of time and
money and at Read the Docs we believe we can help significantly here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="top-hiring-channels"&gt;Top hiring channels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was no big surprise to hear that &lt;strong&gt;referrals were the top hiring
channel&lt;/strong&gt;. The second best channel was a bit of a surprise with local
meetups and local communities being very high in a majority of
interviews although this was less true among the largest companies we
talked to. Companies also had some success with recruiting at
conferences, using various job sites, and proactive outreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiring managers shared strategies with us that they used to increase the
number of referral and community candidates they got. Two different
companies we talked to hosted multiple local meetups at their offices
and one of those hiring managers said "being plugged into the
community" was their main channel for hiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another hiring manager who focused a lot on developers with security
experience talked about having "LinkedIn parties" where either a
hiring manager or internal recruiter sat with engineers on their team
one-on-one to go through their LinkedIn network. Even when he heard a
person "is great, but they'll never change jobs", that was a good
candidate to target. Security is such a high demand field, he said, that
very few great people are actively looking for a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2019-job-seeker-timeline.png" class="mw-100" alt="Job seeker timeline"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reaching-people-who-arent-looking-is-critical"&gt;Reaching people who aren't looking is critical&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our biggest takeaways from the interviews was that companies
wanted to reach candidates before they started actively looking. Most of
the hiring managers we talked to stressed the importance of getting in
front of passive candidates. Certainly fewer people are actively looking
for developer jobs than those who are just open to a change. A few
different reasons were given but I actually think &lt;a href="https://www.inc.com/magazine/20070501/column-guest.html"&gt;Joel Spolsky had it
right&lt;/a&gt; when he
said top developers "barely ever apply for jobs at all. That's because
they already have jobs."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote isn't necessarily a slight against people who apply actively
to jobs. Virtually everyone I know in tech started their career applying
to a job. Rather, the message here is that as a developer becomes a
mid-level developer and then becomes a senior developer, they are more
likely to rely on their network to somewhat passively job seek rather
than going through the front door and simply applying on a company
website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaching people who aren't actively looking is one area where Read the
Docs can really help. Companies want to reach them when they are just
thinking about a new job or perhaps passively seeking. Developers who
come to our site are actively building software, not job-seeking. Many
of them are content at their current position. For those that aren't,
this is a perfect place to showcase great companies and help Read the
Docs' visitors to find their next job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="recruiters-can-be-worth-it"&gt;Recruiters can be worth it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In each interview, we asked whether the company used recruiters or
recruiting related services (eg. Hired, Triplebyte). Universally, hiring
managers brought up how expensive recruiters are, but most of the people
we talked to who had actually used recruiters in the past had a positive
impression overall. Hiring takes a ton of time, typically from senior
folks at the company. At smaller startups, that's frequently the CEO or
CTO. Even though the price is high, recruiters who help speed that
process along are worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the quote that really summed it up was from a VP of engineering
at a startup that just raised a Series B. He's trying to grow his team
by 10 developers this year (about a 50% increase). His experience hiring
his first couple developers through a 2-person boutique recruiting firm
was great and he would use them for hiring everyone "if hiring 10
people didn't mean $100k+" in fees alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure: &lt;a href="https://triplebyte.com"&gt;Triplebyte&lt;/a&gt; is an advertiser
on Read the Docs. We're fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="diversity-and-inclusivity-in-hiring"&gt;Diversity and inclusivity in hiring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't ask any questions around hiring for diversity but fully six
hiring managers volunteered information on their companies' strategies
for getting more diverse candidates. This is why I love this kind of
interview where the goal is just to listen to what hiring managers say
and dig deeper when you hear something interesting. Some of the larger
companies we talked to had explicit diversity goals set at the company
level. Even among the hiring managers at smaller companies, they shared
some tactics they used to get more diverse candidates to apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the companies with hard diversity goals, most of them told us that
their strategy entailed syndicating their job openings to diversity
focused jobs sites or in some cases engaging directly with relevant
interest groups. In terms of efficacy, reviews of these various jobs
boards was mixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the more positive side, hiring managers cited Girl Develop It, Black
Girls Code, and PyLadies as fantastic channels for &lt;strong&gt;both increasing
candidate diversity and for high quality applicants&lt;/strong&gt;. Two companies
also talked about trying to decrease bias in their job postings using
&lt;a href="https://textio.com/"&gt;Textio&lt;/a&gt; and similar services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having multiple people mention diversity completely unprompted really
shows that this topic is becoming higher priority for companies and
hiring managers. It also shows that it if hiring for diversity is
important to your company, you need to have a plan for actually making
those goals a reality. It's worth checking whether the strategy
actually works too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="remember-sourcing-is-the-bigger-problem"&gt;Remember, sourcing is the bigger problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every single hiring manager we talked to complained about the time they
spent filtering resumes from applicants. Some choice quotes I heard
included "95% of applicants weren't a fit" even after only reviewing
the resume and a hiring manager who posted to a very popular remote-only
job board told me he got "literally one thousand applications". While
I believe this is a legitimate complaint, I think &lt;a href="http://blog.alinelerner.com/building-a-product-in-the-technical-recruiting-space-read-this-first/"&gt;Aline Lerner, founder
of interviewing.io said it
best&lt;/a&gt;
when she said "Engineering hiring isn't a filtering problem. It's a
sourcing problem." The reason we heard it a lot is that filtering is a
very time-consuming task that hiring managers directly deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real problem here is that &lt;strong&gt;the number of applicants to a job post
is a vanity metric&lt;/strong&gt;. What hiring managers are looking for is qualified
applicants, which is harder to gauge without some additional work. One
of the problems here is that a lot of jobs sites make it really easy for
candidates to apply to lots of jobs. This is understandable from their
perspective as more applicants makes their platform seem more valuable.
There's no reason for a job board to put artificial barriers into the
application funnel, but hiring managers told us they want candidates who
want to work for their company not somebody who is applying to every job
out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of building product here, I think hiring managers just need a
few tweaks to get more of a signal of candidate quality and intent in
their applications. A few of the hiring managers we talked to described
how they did this. Multiple hiring managers mentioned how they required
a cover letter that answered specific questions ("why us" was the most
popular). Another hiring manager described how his hiring system just
asked a few short questions of candidates -- for example, "what is the
software project you're most proud of" -- when they applied. When a
candidate didn't do a cover letter or didn't answer the questions,
they weren't considered. The latter solution seemed like the best of
both worlds as it solves the one-click apply problem without being too
much of a barrier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thanks"&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to thank all the hiring managers who took time out of their
days (or in some cases evenings) to talk to us. If you're a hiring
manager or an internal company recruiter and you'd like to share your
experiences and help Read the Docs, please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@readthedocs.org?subject=Lessons+From+Hiring+Managers+Post"&gt;get in
touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check back soon for our
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2019/02/tips-for-getting-a-developer-interview/"&gt;next post in this series&lt;/a&gt;
which covers tips for candidates based on the same interviews!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you hiring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertisers/hiring/"&gt;Get in front of passive candidates already using your tech&lt;/a&gt;
by promoting your job openings with Read the Docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="hiring"></category><category term="readthedocs"></category></entry><entry><title>Tips to Hire Developers with Read the Docs</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/10/tips-to-hire-developers-with-read-the-docs/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2018-10-30:/blog/2018/10/tips-to-hire-developers-with-read-the-docs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/hiring-developers-with-readthedocs/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the Docs is probably not the first place …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/hiring-developers-with-readthedocs/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the Docs is probably not the first place you think of if you are
recruiting. However, over &lt;strong&gt;7 million unique developers use Read the
Docs each month&lt;/strong&gt; from all over the world. We didn't set out to build a
better job board, but after a number of advertisers used our &lt;a href="https://docs.readthedocs.io/en/latest/advertising/ethical-advertising.html"&gt;ethical
ads&lt;/a&gt;
for recruiting, we discovered that Read the Docs was a great place to
find developer talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hiring-with-read-the-docs-works"&gt;Hiring with Read the Docs works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers are not always actively job seeking by browsing job boards or
company careers pages. However, they are on Read the Docs reading about
the libraries and frameworks they use. Even when people aren't actively
looking for a new job, many are open to exploring new opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Read the Docs, we found that developers engage with hiring ads at a
higher rate than any other kind of advertising. With hiring ads,
developers get ads that are relevant and interesting and companies reach
the folks actively using the tech they are recruiting for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2018-ctr-adtype.png" class="mw-100" alt="Click-through rate by ad type Q3 2018"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="be-specific-and-find-the-right-developers"&gt;Be specific and find the right developers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for Python developers, you can configure your hiring
ad to only show on Python related documentation. You can further refine
your audience to Read the Docs visitors in specific regions. Whether you
are looking for a remote Python data scientist or a blockchain developer
in Switzerland, be as specific as possible. This ensures you don't get
unqualified candidates as well as making sure you catch the eyes of the
people you are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="set-the-right-expectations"&gt;Set the right expectations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any type of advertising, setting appropriate expectations can make
the difference between a lackluster and successful campaign. In hiring,
it is even more critical. This means making sure that your hiring ad for
a front-end JavaScript developer links directly to your JavaScript
developer job listing page where people can click "apply". Don't link
to a listing of all of your open positions unless your hiring ad sets
that expectation. Nothing is worse for the developer than clicking on a
hiring ad and not knowing what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, some things can set the wrong kind of expectation. Most
developers have seen enough hiring posts for "rockstars" and
"ninjas" to know what to expect. Be honest and upfront and you will
attract the right folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="stand-out"&gt;Stand out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers get contacted all the time by recruiters and it can be
difficult to show prospective employees why they should check out your
company. People look for all sorts of different things when seeking a
new job from working with a high-caliber team to working for a company
whose goals they agree with. You should highlight your best selling
points right on your hiring ad as early as possible. If your company
affords a fantastic work/life balance, mention that. A company in a
great location, with a beautiful office, and top of the line hardware
should definitely feature that. Focusing on your best attributes shows
you care about your developers and helps you appeal to people who care
about your products and mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you hiring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertisers/hiring/"&gt;Find qualified candidates&lt;/a&gt;
already using your tech by promoting your job openings with Read the Docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category></entry><entry><title>Update on Ad Blocking and Acceptable Ads</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/05/update-on-ad-blocking-and-acceptable-ads/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2018-05-21:/blog/2018/05/update-on-ad-blocking-and-acceptable-ads/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ad-blocker-update/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, we shared about the
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/05/ads-and-ad-blockers/"&gt;challenge …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ad-blocker-update/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, we shared about the
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/05/ads-and-ad-blockers/"&gt;challenge ad blocking presented to our sustainability&lt;/a&gt;
and what we were doing about it. On May 4th, Read the Docs
was added to the &lt;a href="https://acceptableads.com/"&gt;Acceptable Ads list&lt;/a&gt;
meaning that our visitors running ad blockers who choose to allow
unintrusive advertising will see our ads again. The &lt;strong&gt;impact to our ad
views, clicks, and revenue was immediate&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="data-on-our-inclusion-in-the-acceptable-ads-list"&gt;Data on our inclusion in the Acceptable Ads list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2018-readthedocs-adblocker-update.png" class="mw-100" alt="Impact of ad blocking and acceptable ads at Read the Docs"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;32% of Read the Docs visitors run an ad blocker&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimates around the web vary regarding what percentage of people
run ad blockers and it varies heavily by industry. We discussed this
figure a bit in our
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/05/ads-and-ad-blockers/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;It took a month from application to inclusion in the list&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discovered about our inclusion in the
&lt;a href="https://easylist.to/"&gt;EasyList&lt;/a&gt; ad blocker list within a couple
days and immediately applied to the Acceptable Ads program. No
changes were required of us to meet the &lt;a href="https://acceptableads.com/en/about/criteria"&gt;Acceptable Ads
criteria&lt;/a&gt; and we also
qualified for &lt;a href="https://adblockplus.org/en/acceptable-ads#privacy-friendly-acceptable-ads"&gt;Acceptable Ads without third-party
tracking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Eyeo, the company behind AdBlock Plus, derives &lt;a href="https://adblockplus.org/about#monetization"&gt;most of their
revenue&lt;/a&gt; from the
Acceptable Ads initiative by charging large entities, Read the Docs
&lt;strong&gt;did not&lt;/strong&gt; pay for inclusion on the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Over half of those running an ad blocker allow acceptable ads&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given our more tech-savvy and privacy-focused audience, we didn't
know what to expect. Not every ad blocker allows acceptable ads by
default and even then users can choose to turn them off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;People running ad blockers DO click on ads&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can definitively say this is true of our audience. Our
click-through rate did not change based on ad blocking or our
inclusion in the acceptable ads list at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the ad views and clicks blocked by ad blockers, inclusion in the
Acceptable Ads list meant that 55-60% of our ad-blocking visitors choose
to allow our ads. This directly translated into revenue toward our
sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="building-our-ethical-ads"&gt;Building our Ethical Ads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Acceptable Ads list is definitely a step in the right direction for
us. We share the goal of unintrusive advertising that respects our
audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People understand that advertising funds much of the web. As ads got
larger, more annoying, and ad networks stored more information on
millions of people, however, many people finally decided to install ad
blockers.
This is the &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-graph/how-to-reverse-publisher-revenue-drain-c33e41bf0665"&gt;largest boycott in human
history&lt;/a&gt;
and blaming users isn't the answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on our experience with ad blocking and the Acceptable Ads list, it
is clear that visitors will allow advertising that doesn't disrupt user
experience and doesn't track people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are glad to have made progress toward regaining our sustaining
revenue. Read the Docs is continuing on our experiment to fund open
source infrastructure in a way that is a win/win for all parties, and we
are glad you're following along with us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="adblock"></category><category term="readthedocs"></category></entry><entry><title>Ads and Ad blockers</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/05/ads-and-ad-blockers/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>David Fischer</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2018-05-02:/blog/2018/05/ads-and-ad-blockers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ads-and-adblocking/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time, we shared how
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/04/ethical-advertising-works/"&gt;ethical advertising works&lt;/a&gt;
to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ads-and-adblocking/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time, we shared how
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/04/ethical-advertising-works/"&gt;ethical advertising works&lt;/a&gt;
to keep Read the Docs sustainable without creepy ad
targeting. This time, we will share about one of our biggest challenges
with advertising. At the beginning of April, Read the Docs was added to
one of the most popular ad block lists: the
&lt;a href="https://easylist.to/"&gt;Easylist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ad-blocker-fallout"&gt;Ad blocker fallout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ethicalads.io/images/posts/2018-readthedocs-adblocker-fallout.png" class="mw-100" alt="Effect of ad blocking on Read the Docs ad views"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting added to the EasyList had a significant and immediate impact on
the bottom line at Read the Docs. Right around April 1, &lt;strong&gt;32% of our ad
views simply vanished&lt;/strong&gt;. At first, we thought we had done something
horribly wrong but then we discovered that this was due entirely to ad
blocking. Our actual traffic wasn't down at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users' browsers were simply downloading the updated EasyList which
blocked ads on Read the Docs. In terms of ad viewership, weekdays --
our busiest days and the peaks in the graph -- became more like weekends
and weekends fell off a cliff. We had always guessed what percentage of
our user base ran ad blockers. Now we know. We knew this day would come
as we became more successful but we had hoped it was a ways off
considering we weren't part of a large ad network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This directly affected our operations and staff. Our operating costs
didn't go down in any significant way, but revenue sure did.
Advertising is by far the largest source of revenue at Read the Docs and
it just dropped by about a third. This meant that we had to cut some
costs where we could and slow down some hiring plans. While Read the
Docs is not a non-profit company, all the revenue is reinvested into the
project itself, paying maintainers, and other places in the open source
ecosystem. The situation is not dire by any means, but it was certainly
disappointing that we ended up on the same list with popup advertisers
who couldn't care less about privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="all-about-ad-blockers"&gt;All about ad blockers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ad blockers fulfill a legitimate need to mitigate the &lt;a href="https://docs.readthedocs.io/en/latest/ethical-advertising.html"&gt;significant
downsides of
advertising&lt;/a&gt;
from tracking across the internet, security implications of third-party
code, and impacting the UX and performance of sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Read the Docs, we specifically didn't want those things. That's why
we built the ad network we wanted to exist with only relevant ads and no
creepy behavioral targeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a &lt;a href="https://pagefair.com/downloads/2017/01/PageFair-2017-Adblock-Report.pdf"&gt;2017 report from
PageFair&lt;/a&gt;
(pdf), a company that specializes in quantifying ad blocking, 11% of
global web users run an ad blocker. Considering that Read the Docs'
core audience is tech-savvy, privacy-conscious developers, it should be
no surprise that our number is higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-are-we-doing-about-it"&gt;What are we doing about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will be an uphill battle to get back to where we were in terms of
revenue and sustaining Read the Docs, here are a few things we are
working on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We applied to the &lt;a href="https://acceptableads.com/"&gt;acceptable ads&lt;/a&gt; list,
    an ad block list enabled on many ad blockers by default that enables
    some unobtrusive advertising. We are very hopeful here but it does
    take quite a bit longer to get on this list than it does to get
    blocked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nagging users into allowing ads on Read the Docs. We are envisioning
    more of a polite nag in a similar vein to
    &lt;a href="https://jsfiddle.net/"&gt;jsfiddle&lt;/a&gt; rather than an \"adblock wall\"
    which prevents usage of Read the Docs until it's allowed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blogging and raising awareness of how ad blocking affects us and
    other open source projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we could simply change our CSS and ad API to avoid blocking since
we host our ads ourselves, we decided not to engage in a cat and mouse
game since this work would not benefit users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advertising funds much of the web and many people recognize that while
there are plenty of bad actors in the ad industry -- think pop-under ad
networks or ads that navigate your browser for you -- some advertising
is necessary to power the web we know and love especially when it comes
to open source software which has &lt;a href="https://www.fordfoundation.org/library/reports-and-studies/roads-and-bridges-the-unseen-labor-behind-our-digital-infrastructure/"&gt;unique funding
challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: On May 4th, Read the Docs was added to the acceptable ads
list! We will collect data over the next couple weeks and have a
follow-up post on what effects this had on advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="open-source-advertising-list"&gt;Open source advertising list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Read the Docs, we also discovered that we are not the only open
source project that got our advertising blocked by ad blockers. Many
open source projects that fund themselves through advertising get
blocked and some of them don't have the resources to navigate the
acceptable ads program or understand the inner workings of ad blockers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, some web users may not want to allow all acceptable ads which
includes many ads from the big networks but we are hoping they would be
willing to accept ads that benefit their community of software
developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are launching a &lt;strong&gt;new initiative&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;a href="https://ads-for-open-source.readthedocs.io"&gt;allow advertising that
benefits open source
software&lt;/a&gt;. We encourage you
to subscribe to the this list and support open source. If you run an
open source project affected by ad blockers, we would love to help you
too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="adblock"></category><category term="readthedocs"></category></entry><entry><title>Ethical Advertising Works</title><link href="https://www.ethicalads.io/blog/2018/04/ethical-advertising-works/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-16T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Eric Holscher</name></author><id>tag:www.ethicalads.io,2018-04-16:/blog/2018/04/ethical-advertising-works/</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ethical-advertising-works/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been two years since we first launched …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post first appeared
on the &lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ethical-advertising-works/"&gt;Read the Docs company blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been two years since we first launched
&lt;a href="https://blog.readthedocs.com/ads-on-read-the-docs/"&gt;ads on Read the Docs&lt;/a&gt;.
We figured it was time to report on the results that we've
seen, and say thanks to those who have helped us along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-results"&gt;The Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it simply: &lt;strong&gt;Ethical Advertising works&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Q1 2018, our estimated revenue from advertising is $75,000. This is
enough to fund our small team of 4 people to work on Read the Docs
full-time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we started building our ethical advertising model, we didn't know
how it would work out. We didn't know much about the ad industry, and
we were doing things different than everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are happy to report that you can build advertising that is a
win/win/win for all parties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the Docs wins because we generate revenue, allowing us to
    sustain our operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advertisers win because they are able to reach our audience of
    developers, helping to grow their business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users win because their privacy is maintained, and they continue to
    have access to our service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethical advertising on Read the Docs has not been without its
challenges, which we will cover in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tracking-users-isnt-required"&gt;Tracking users isn't required&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way we've been trying to prove a simple thesis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can have successful advertising without tracking our users. So much
of the trouble facing the ad industry these days is because of this
massive databases of user data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been able to show that we can show ads without knowing exactly
who our users are. The content they are reading is enough to show them
targeted ads, without knowing anything about them. Specifically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do not let advertisers run 3rd party code on Read the Docs. Ad
    images and javascript is all hosted by us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do not provide advertisers with data dumps, except aggregated
    reports on the clicks and views their ads got.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We target our ads based only on geography and the details of the
    page being visited, not on a profile of the user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're now taking a look at what we've learned, and how we might help
more infrastructure projects reach sustainability with an ethical
advertising approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="towards-an-ethical-ad-network"&gt;Towards an Ethical Ad Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We have shown that an advertising business model that respects users
can also sustain critical open source infrastructure.&lt;/strong&gt; We hope that we
can act as an example for other projects that depend on ads. You can
make money without giving away your users data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers have the power to shift the ad industry to respect user
privacy. We must start with our own projects, leading by example. We
need to have all the ads in the open source ecosystem respect user
privacy, and then we can start to apply pressure to other parts of the
tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We realize that not every open source project can do all the work that
we've done. We want to explore how we can build an &lt;strong&gt;Ethical Ad
Network&lt;/strong&gt;, where user data isn't sent to us, but each project doesn't
need to do ad sales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ethical ad network is still in the planning phases, but if you know
a project that might be interested in being a beta tester, please &lt;a href="mailto:ads@readthedocs.org"&gt;get
in touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="thanks"&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to thank all of companies who have believed in our ethical ads
initiative. You can only sell something if people buy it, and I'd like
to give credit to the folks who have believed in our concept:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twilio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sentry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollbar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stream&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Dog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mongo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hosted Graphite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Level 12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pyup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Triplebyte&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Digital Impact Alliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exoscale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nginx&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Odoo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CircleCI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cherry Servers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uniregistry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OSCON&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want your company to be on the list? You can get more information on our
&lt;a href="https://www.ethicalads.io/advertisers/"&gt;advertising page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="readthedocs"></category></entry></feed>